but you are often uh referring that we
should go back to the sutas actually
what is written in the suas is that is
that kind of is is that your uh person
approach or there is a how should I say
a school should I call it within s
within because uh something like used to
be in ancient time like this group sanas
they they were referring also suas they
didn't they didn't uh recognize Abid
dama and other other uh right well I
think it's just a question of label you
know I'm sure there are few more monks
they would agree with me in that in
terms of going back to the sutas and not
trusting the later Abid dama in
commentaries but I wouldn't say there is
a school of us that we go together and
decideed that it's more like just
individuals on the base of the practice
so that that makes more sense and it's
least risky and also so that like you
know the latest stuff it's it's often
contradicting what it would have said
and therefore you can't trust
it in regard to what is said now can you
give us some advises how to do uh meta
bana how to do meta meditation because
it seems to me that U it is uh very
related uh what you mentioned to to
accept everything as it is and uh you
know how to say to um to to regard to to
everything what is happen to us
happening to us with a kind of positive
attitude uh however
during uh uh uh usual uh during usual
description of of mea meditation very
often it said that uh we we supposed to
develop some kind of love or or positive
emotions uh towards the you know our
surroundings and everything what is
happening but uh it seems to me that uh
it should be uh more like you mentioned
before just to be open and to accept uh
everything what is happening so I would
really appreciate if you could say a few
words about the meta meditation and
especially I'm interested uh would you
recommend to do like all four uh stages
all for all four kinds like meta mudita
Etc or we could we should focus only on one
or we could we should focus only on one
and then other would come naturally
thank you yeah yeah so first that's uh
what you described as commonly meta as
commonly thought is not meta really you
read the sutas there is no spreading of
love and so on it's spreading of non-ill
Will and there's no spreading either
it's more like expanding your mind so to
include everything else so there is no
basis for real
will so when the mind is expanded in in
a sense that it cannot resist anything
good or bad there is no basis for hatred
to arise impossible because the
necessary basis for manifestation of any
particular hatred is resistance is
refusal to accept it if the mind is so
expanded that it that it cannot resist
anything anymore it's cannot resist this
body other bodies in any direction of
the world then there is no basis for
hatred and that's the pure meta non ill
will as I say often opposite love is not
opposite of ill will love is opposite of
non- Love ill will is opposite of
non-ill will so in other words if you practice
will so in other words if you practice
meta you will abandon both love and ill
will and as as for the four stages
they're not four stages it's one
practice that you can take on like
higher levels and there are four of them
so you start developing the first meta
through that you will develop second
through that you will develop third
through that you can develop fourth just
like janas you don't do one two three
four but it's within establishing
yourself in in first J you then get to
develop the second
one so within developing meta you then
get to develop karuna UPA eventually in
the end but it's not a matter of choice
hey let me develop UPA and Equanimity
now that's impossible because the mind
is affected by ill will and everything
else so that's how if you want meta to
do it in non-abstract
sense you just have to stop resisting
yourself here feelings that you have
perceptions that you have stop acting
towards Pleasant ones and stop resisting
the uncomfortable ones and that's always
why every meta starts with yourself not
by spreading love to yourself but by
developing non-resistance in regard to
yourself if you don't resist these five
senses if you don't act out of these
five senses you cannot resist or act out
towards anything that comes on account
of them that it's second to them which
is other people in the
world what do you think about this
vasana what is which is thought by goka
group you know what would be what would
be your comment on this practice I'm
interested thank M it's a it's a wrong
wrong direction of the effort because
it's based it's a practice that's based
on observation of things observation of
your senses observation of Sensations
which are basically bodily touches
internal or
external it's not based on uh
understanding of the context
understanding of your
intentions um understanding of the state
of mind because you expect just things
to be shown to you through
observation not through effort to
understand so it's ultimately a
different direction from where the dhama
is that's why budha said when he
described for example walking meditation
he didn't say you walk by feeling the SS
of your feet and knees bending and so on
he said walking up and down I purify my
mind from UNH wholesome States that's
the instruction what is the UNH
wholesome State well lust is UN
wholesome State greed is UN wholesome
State jealous is UN wholesome State Envy
ill will irrit ation hatred all of those
are un wholesome States but what the
person does on account of it let's watch
Sensations so that they will magically
dispel our UNH wholesome States no I am
the one responsible for UNH wholesome
States so you do the walking or sitting
because it's a repetitive or still
action so it doesn't take too much of
your attention to do it because you need
all of your attention and focus in a
sense of context and mindfulness towards
recognizing the mental states that there
that you are subjected under and there
is no technique for
that that's just effort based on the
instruction and correct information that
sends you that way and tells you that's
what you need to look
for yes but when you are siing enough
long enough and observing such
Sensations then uh as a as a result of
it you can also learn a lot of your mind
how it works about your motivations
about resistance about everything what
you are talking about no you learned
that because I told you that's what you
need to
learn if you were to start for example
if vasana is truly vasana you wouldn't
need all of this I'm telling you you
would simply watch your Sensations and
arrive at the same conclusions and you
don't the only reason you arrive at the
conclusions of I need to see my
intention I need to understand this I
need to practice sense restraint is cuz
somebody told you you need to do that so
you don't need to watch your Sensations
for the sake of it you just need to not
forget what you have to do that you
already know so if you want to sit quietly or
know so if you want to sit quietly or
walk up and down do so contemplating
what you need to do you must and Buddha
says what you need to do he said you
should not tolerate thoughts of
sensuality thoughts of ill will thoughts
of hatred you should not welcome
entertain encourage them to stay longer
you should not act out of them that's
what you need to do
it's just when people see they already
know this from the sutas and from the
instruction then they do this uh
sensation watching or whatever else that
kind of results in in calmness or
whatever else which is fine same like
you know lay down and relax if you
attend it's a valid experience but
because you know you were taught that
there is much more to it you end up
ascribing all these values such as you
know seeing my motivation intention to
that we pass in the practice it has
nothing to do it the only reason you
know that the mental states of ill will
is are bad is because you were told they
were bad you thought about it you saw
for yourself that they are bad and they
cause you suffering sensation watching
had nothing to do with it and if you
still are doubtful about it as I said
take the experiment of somebody who
hasn't been told about the value of
virtue sense strength and mindfulness
and give them the sensation watching
will they arrive at the same values not
the chance not in a million years
because watching sensation is nothing
other than watching bodily touches or
listening to the sounds of the ear
basically keeping the mind on the level
of the
senses not on the level of the nature
behind the senses that you need to
understand that's why it doesn't matter
how you breathe how you walk what
matters is to be aware of the mental
States in regard to your breathing in
regard to your walking are they
wholesome are they UNH wholesome am I
welcoming them am I delighting in them
am I ignoring them am I fearing them and
so
on so that's the work that's the true
repas
understanding because if it were if the
wisdom were on the level of the senses
the Buddha would have said so he would
say just sit down feeling the sensations
in your body and wisdom will arise no he
said sit down and understand the nature
of the body within your
body understand the nature of feelings
within your feelings the nature of Mind
within your mind the nature of thoughts
within your thoughts how do you
understand well for example by
contemplating death in regard to the
body by contemplating subject to change
in regard to the body that's how you
practice mindfulness of the
body when the when when you do the the
um the repas of the of the mind you
don't watch the sensations or moment to
moment passing awareness or whatever
else no he says you know mind affected
with lust as mind affected with lust so
you endure it you don't act out of it
you don't Delight in it you don't
welcome it he knows mind affected with
anger as mind affected with
anger and then he watches the physical
no then he doesn't lose the sight of the
Mind affected with anger until that
anger disappears and then he spent the
time enduring the angry mind without
acting out of that angry mind and
without welcoming delighting in it
entertaining it prolonging it making it
work worse that's how you train that
internal immovability in regard to the
states of Mind feeling and the positions
of the
body so in that sense that's what I mean
it's completely the opposite direction
from the direction of sense observation
feeling touching looking sensing hearing
and so
on um would you say that this is this is
the um could be an introduction
introductory State no start medit
no intro introduction is learning about
a precept sense
restraint value of seclusion mindfulness
that's your introduction no that's not
what I meant when you sit um and you try
to well the Buddha says um that the B
enters and dwells in in the first J Etc
so maybe this would be like a way just a
method to Cal the Mind down to bring it
back what what would be the method to
come the Mind down to watch the
sensations um no well that's cuz that
that's not where the mind is why would
watching the the sense touches of your
body or just for the first couple of
minutes maybe well again like yeah sure
so if you need to calm down if you need
to calm down if you were sort of busy or
agitated yeah calm down but that's but
that's not no that's not how the pass is
advertised isn't it they don't say oh
this is a mere relaxation technique for
which you know have a back massage lay
down sleep a bit wake up relax go for a
walk and then start doing the work no no
no it's advertised as the work watching
sensation leads to Enlightenment and
that's simply not the case no I had a
followup question uh bante how would you
characterize the distinction between a a
sensation uh being aware of Sensations
then B contemplation uh as reflective
awareness in mindfulness as you describe
it and C intellection regular thinking
what would be helpful ways of thinking
about these three phenomena or processes
well sensation is basically you need to
undo all the mistaken views B sensation
is almost regarded as if it's a sort of
feeling but Sensations in reality is
just a physical sense of touch
experienced internally and that's why it's always
internally and that's why it's always
measured as or I'm feeling it in my
knees or my back or my belly it feels
like this feel it doesn't feel you're
perceiving it so it's a mere sense of
touch when you sit on a chair you have a
sensation where you're leaning on the
chair or if there is sensation of ants
in my arms for whatever reason whether I
pin the nerve or something doesn't
matter the point is Sensations are on
the level of sight sound smell taste
touches there is nothing more to them
there are there is no special property
of Sensations that somehow magically
reveals you the truth
what was the second one uh contemplation
uh reflective awareness in mindfulness
as you describe it and then the third
was intellection regular things okay
well let me start with the third one
third one is the intellect it's using
your own reasoning like this you realize
wait a minute these things that I read
today that say Buddhist Meditation is I
don't find in the sutas so the Buddha
and the meditation that's mentioned in
the sutas does not quite match the
meditation you read about today so you
use your reason to recognize there is a
problem there you can't have it both
ways if they're not saying the same
thing well only one of them is then
right they can't be both
right so you use your intellect to
discern where uh the quality of
information let's say like that the the
the the accuracy of the information
you're collecting about the
practice and then the second one the
contemplation and reflexive awareness is
exactly that
then seeing it in practice seeing it in
your life seeing it in your states of
Mind Not Mere
[Music] Theory that's why really Buddhist
Theory that's why really Buddhist
Meditation should be Buddhist
contemplation because the idea of mind
you meditation even in Christianity
means that means recollecting you know
thinking about the God and so on but
today when you say meditation means
concentrating focusing until I'm unaware
of everything else and I'm one pointed
where nothing else exists and I said
that many times that that the Buddha
himself described that in the sutas as
as a completely wrong meditation that he
compared to like a animal sort of
waiting for a for a a cat waiting for a
mouse to pounce it on it's so
concentrated the whole world disappears
just sees one thing and that's
completely the the M samadi the wrong
direction of your
samadi so contemplation will
basically uh make you think rightly and
uh discern that right direction I'm
talking about on the basis of rightly
selected information because if you were
if you heard wrongly you will not be
able to arrive at the right conclusions
because you don't have the right
instruction and right
pointers how would you describe right
samadi she said you just mentioned wrong
Sam uhuh well right of is that uh purifying
uhuh well right of is that uh purifying
your mind from the UN wholesome state
so when the last is present for
example not not welcoming it not acting
out of it not trying to get rid of it
not trying to explain it or justify it
or avoid responsibility for it enduring
it rightly is the right samadi so if you
learn how to endure things without
acting out of it you are practicing
samadi and that's exactly what the
Buddha described in the sutas he said
samadi is when things try to move the
Monk's mind but the Monk's mind doesn't
move on account of things trying to move
it that's how he developed samadi he
didn't say samadi is when he gets so
focused on his nostrils the whole world
disappears so it's immovability in
regard to things that want to move you
so see you are already practicing Samar
in a day-to-day life want whether you
want it or not cuz you are already
forced to endure things whether you want
it or not the problem is without the
right instruction you will not
necessarily learn on account of that
endurance but if you know as I said how
to endure things on that right level
that will result in that irreversible
wisdom yeah I thought the fourth J was
synonymous with right Sam no the first J
is already synonymous with right
Sam that's already yeah yeah okay but
see what is the first of all that right
concentration means right samadi so it's
just whoever translated that chose the
word conation we choose composure so
right composure is the first
J um so yes the first Jana is the the is
the measure of your correct samadi but
there are you know quite a bit of
development before the first J that goes
in the direction of right samadi but it
doesn't quite constitute the the first J
yet because for soana he doesn't need to
have Jan to get the right
view but he does need to grasp the signs
of his mind as we spoke before that is a
necessary prerequisite for developing
the Right View and there is no right
samadi without the Right View so gaining
the right view means soap already has a
form of right samadi although he's not
quite on the level of Jana
yet uh we often talk about uh about this
activity of preparing to some situations
uhhuh uh but uh sometimes uh as I
observe my my life and my inner
[Music] inner processes and so on uh happening
inner processes and so on uh happening
at the moment uh often you are s
surprised by the the complexity and by
the the magnitude of some emotions that
appear and that you are not aware that
they will appear MH so you can't prepare
to
them and I I can observe uh at at this
particular uh case when some uh life or
some processes are coming to an
end and as close as you are to an end
there comes uh in my case a big big um
big bag of guil mhm and how how can you
prepare and how do you deal with this uh
big magnit magnitude of emotions when
you when you feel that you have missed
before and now you are only there with a
big guilt and this is you have to deal
with well that's that's the thing you
need to start dealing with smaller
emotions of a smaller magnitude before
they get that big it can't it doesn't
get that big on its own it gets that big
because you've been ignoring all the
small signs and tokens they were
pointing that it's going to get that big
so if you have been ignoring and now
you're facing a big guilt well the first
thing you have to do is not act out of
it and endure it until it ceases and
then learn your lesson from it in a
sense that remember now how big that
guilt was and how unpleasant so next
time don't wait that long don't let it
get that much out of
hand Yeah because sometimes if you ignore and
Yeah because sometimes if you ignore and
you don't contemplate it it can appear
that you uh that you reject this uh
process of uh handling the situation and
it can get you to really deep and dark
places yeah yeah because you turn the
Blind Eye to it that's all you need to
do you don't need to like figure out
guilt before it comes you just need to
recognize that it always remain as a
possibility so you don't ignore that
possibility of eventual discomfort uh
pain and resistance to it and then you
learn how to not resist to that how to
endure it and not act out of it and
that's how it will cease to pressure
you yeah and that's also how you will
not lose perspective when guilt arises
you will see whether it's a rational
guilt or irrational guilt whether it's a
guilt rooted in something that you
genuinely did wrong or not rooted in
anything you did wrong but just your own
mind winding you up and attacking
you but what happens when you're faced
with situations that where you can't
change the the I mean if some people are
gone how can you change
the what you have done wrong in the past
you can't you can stop resisting the
guilt here and now that's how you free
yourself from those actions that's how
anguli Mala freed himself from all the
murders he
committed he became an Aran Here and Now
he couldn't change he couldn't undo his
actions but he did finally resolve the
root of all action which is craving in
regard to feeling and because of that
none of those actions actually followed
him any
further because the only reason you
would want
to even theoretically try and change the
past is because you don't want to endure
the present
guilt so stop resisting the present
guilt and past will cease to be a
problem
could bant perhaps share a few more
words on how to deal with guilt how to
accept the previous mistakes paths not
taken wrong paths Etc how to stop
resisting guilt if there's time all
right well see you would all of those
things you would want to do because you
don't want to feel guilt so you would
have to accept past mistakes so I don't
feel bad today on account of past
mistakes so in other words your
acceptance of past mistakes is fueling
your guilt because of which you want to
accept the past mistakes so it's a
vicious circle so the only way to do it
is to stop U to endure the discomfort
first you just have to endure
it stop resisting it stop trying to
accept the past stop trying to um come
to terms with it because all of that is
rooted in you still resisting the
presently enduring discomfort of the
guilt so if you first stop doing
everything or anything on account of it
and endure it then you'll see where to
go then you'll see that within that not
nonresistance you can get to look closer
at that guilt which is there and the
only reason it hurts is because you
resist it in itself it doesn't it doesn't cause
it in itself it doesn't it doesn't cause
you pain like a hot burning embers don't
hurt unless you know you reach out with
your hand to grab
them so that that's the
point stop reaching out so how do you
stop reaching out well by enduring the
pain first to see where what causes it
directly the present pain is not caused
by things you did in the past things
done to you in the past things you
missed in the past opportunities you
whatever else you didn't seiz and so on
present pain is caused by present resist
present resistance to a present feeling
that's it that's the first Noble Truth
the root of suffering is not the past
it's not the guil it's not who said what
said when they said it it's basically
tanha in regard to what you feel that's
why you suffer there and
then so if you really want to take it in
a broader sense it doesn't really matter
what type of feeling there is whether
it's a guilt whether it's a pleasant
feeling the point is you need to learn
how Here and Now not to resist it and
not to indulge
it so how not to lose perspective in
regard to what you feel here and now
that's all really just don't forget
about yourself in regard to how you're
feeling in this present moment and if
you sustain that attitude that's the
basically the P the correct practice of
mindfulness and perspective being deeply
rooted in your gratuitous resistance to
a presently enduring feeling because
feeling is there whether you resist it
or
not so until you stop resisting it it
will bother you
well maybe I have a somewhat related
question not now that I've been
listening to this advice uh it was uh
basically how to improve tolerance to
pain um I mean certain pains I I have no
problems willing de with like if if my
finger hurts it's not a big deal but but
for example uh pain in the head uh I I
find myself quickly grabbing the pills
because it doesn't even allow me to to
think clearly you know there are pains
in the body where your mind remains
intact and there are pains that make it
harder to think and I'm thinking that
this is also probably the reason why the
Toler my tolerance to pain is so low but
uh it's also very hard to um decide and
insist upon it when you're not even
really able to think uh when you're in
the throbs of pain yeah so you have to
decide before before that pain so you
have to anticipate it and then decide
what to do so in this case you know if
it's like a serious life-threatening
pain that might compromise you know your
ability in long term then you address it
but if it's just an uncomfortable
headache that will prevent you to think
for a while and kind of you know make
you numb painful and Confused well
really the reason you're taking the
medicine there is not because of the
pain in the head it's because of the
fear of of losing that Clarity and and
uh levels of management and so
on so in other words it's it's a
psychological cause you're afraid of the
pain that might sort of interfere with
your operation and that scares you and
that's why you take the pill so that's
why you if it's not as I said if it's
just a headache lifethreatening pain not
lifethreatening pain you could just
decide beforehand to not do it and
endure it and experience that discomfort
and confusion and everything else that
comes with it there's no other magical
way what can I do so I don't have to go
through it but get the results of it no
tolerance is developed through
tolerance okay so that's really the
important part is to recognize that
these feelings um enduring of the
feelings will purify you only if you're
enduring them on the right level so if
you're enduring like random feelings and
random discomforts of the physical kind
that that will not do anything
necessarily to you that's why I would
have said you know self mortification
and asceticism is misguided because
people assume that enduring physical
discomforts will somehow lead them you
know to through purification and
everything else but if you endure the
feelings on the right level which is
that mental level see you have to endure
now the pressure to act out of fear in
regard to your headache that will impede
you and complicate your
day so if you endure non-action on the
level of that fear that endurance of
that feeling will actually contribute
towards the purification will contribute
towards strengthening of the mind but if
you're just enduring the pain in your
leg for the sake of a pain in your leg
that's equally
pointless so basically as long as you
get to learn something from it then it's
valuable yeah as long as you see where
where where it is
rooted uh whether it's rooted in sort of
whaty what state of mind is the root of
it and then you endure it on the level
of the state of
mind because if you start seeing it
there then see you realize fear of the
headache is the problem not the headache
in
itself which means you're liable to fear
and it can be caused then by other
things not just the headache so if you
start enduring that feeling on that level not
enduring that feeling on that level not
acting out of it not resisting it you
are actually preparing your mind for any
type of discomfort and unpleasant
confusion and so on that might arise on
account of various circumstances for as
long as you
live I so far I haven't realized that
this was actually there was fear behind
it but it makes sense thank you for this
one [Music]
fear or resistance through having to
psychological resistance through having
to go through that
ordeal so bante
regarding the right contemplation
question uhhuh I I wanted to ask you
before but you already answered me I
wanted to ask you
just practical way how are you dealing
with the for example with the
degradation of your physical and mental
capacity but you
answer the right approaches when you
contemplating that so I just have a like a practical
that so I just have a like a practical
question what is then the the right
contemplation of that how do you
approach this question well yes so any any
this question well yes so any any
Buddhist contemplation can only be
developed on the basis of already
developed virtue and sense restraint
so really if if like if a person is
still struggling with restraining the
senses and upholding the precepts and
sustaining the context of the precepts
and avoiding certain types of action and
so on and
engagements uh that that's what needs to
be developed first because none of these
all of these contemplations will remain
abstract if a person has not created the
basis of virtue the aggregate of virtue
that the Buddha refer to but if you have
created that well then it's kind of it
becomes almost self you are already
going to be more aware of that
um well yeah impermanent nature of your
own because you are not being distracted
anymore through acting out of your
senses and chasing pleasures and um
hiding away from from Pain irrationally
and so on so you're already recognizing
that you are subjected to things and
then all you need to have is a thought
of that and uh death and you'll be
subjected to that because you already
trained your mind to not turn away not
run away not act out of it and that's
the reason why people can't contemplate
death correctly when you think it it
just remains abstract because there is
no basis for it to land or where it does
land where something does remind you of
death inadvertently well you immediately
turn away or try to psychologize it
cover it up explain it just so you don't
endure it on that unpleasant
[Music] level so through development of ches in
level so through development of ches in
sense restraint you are basically
enabling yourself to endure things on
that unpleasant
[Music]
level okay but I think that uh if I
think and contemplate it yes for the
most of the what is going on in people's
lives you can uh can come to the to the
one point where you can understand and
you accept it and so but I think that
this subject of that so
uh so uh how do you say it uh un
recognizable and uh so uh so big thing
that uh I I hope that you come to the to
this one time to this to the point where
you can understand me well that's what
I'm saying
you are closer to contemplating death
when you are practicing sense restraint
than you are when you think about death
on the basis of nonsense
restraint so whether you think about
death or not if you keep the virtue
practice sense restrained don't act
toward sensuality that is already closer
to the contemplation of death
contemplation of
sensation and your idea of contemplation
if it's based on the non-restraint and
non virtue it's not actually that close
it's not it does not stand for that
which death
is because that's why people are so
afraid of giving up Central Pleasures
because it feels like
dying so you want to contemplate death
keep the eight precepts don't act out of
sensuality endure your mind and you're
going to have a firsthand experience or
fading away
uh I have a small question about the the
choices of the words that uh we use when
we talk about contemplation like what is
the difference between contemplation and
introspection is this like the same
would it mean the same thing or is there
a difference to it oh I don't know I
guess it could mean depends really um I
think you just have to explain what you
mean by each term and then see if they
correspond to you but I like I think
contemplation would be I suppose for me
at least uh something
that's based on some sort of instruction
so contemplation is an introspection
with prior
instruction introspection can just be
introspection with all sorts of
instruction or none of
[Music] it okay thank you it's just before I uh
it okay thank you it's just before I uh
was introduced to Buddhism uh I've heard
a lot about introspection and very
little about cont contl and the terms
never connected for me just now I made
the the connection no definitely
definitely contemplation should be a
form of introspection let's say like
that contemplation should not be just
pondering about abstract terms and how
they relate in space and time and what
the connections are and how they
correspond and what are their
similarities contemplation should be
seeing those things introspectively on
the level of that's mean it needs to be
taken personally and seen on that
personal level
thank you